So now I want to talk to you about how
manufacturing transistors evolved go from
sort of the earliest manufactured transistors
to sort of the modern day and how we manufacture
transistors. So the key thing that has made the
difference is transistors started with a certain
size and the goal was to make them smaller
and smaller and package them in different ways
over time. So originally there were individual
transistors connected on a on a circuit board to
other transistors and resistors etc. Then after a
while, we would buy these things called integrated
circuits, IC's, little black things with the legs
on them. And they would have some gates inside
of them, you know, maybe a couple of gates or a
couple of knot gates or a norate or something. And
and the little we could connect up and make use of
these gates by connecting to the little legs. And
then we'd have traces on the underlying medium to
make sure that we connected the right signals to
the right gates. much like we've been doing. Now,
at some point, things changed. So, prior to 1960s,
the transistors were assembled sort of, I'll
show you in a sec, kind of like Lego blocks,
and they were three-dimensional objects. You
would manufacture different materials and then you
would kind of put those materials together like
Lego blocks. In 1960, Fairchild introduced the
2N1613 transistor. And this was manufactured by a
two-dimensional process, meaning that there was a
a a substrate underneath of it. And then they did
stuff on that substrate with manufacturing and
out came a transistor. Instead of like assembling
transistors, they would like lay down transistors
almost like painting transistors versus building
transistors. And this led eventually to very large
scale integration where you could uh in a 3mm x
4mm chunk put 2,300 transistors plus associated
resistors etc. And so that's what led to the the
Intel 404 and which was the first commercially
available single chip microprocessor. The thing
that eventually made this all possible was a thing
called photoiththography. I mentioned that planer
transistors are in effect manufactured almost like
with a paint roller on them, but they weren't
exactly a paint roller. They had these masks so
the paint didn't roll on everywhere. So the paint
rolled on where there were no where there were no
lines. And so we would produce these VLSI layouts
and then we would make in a sense transparencies
with clear areas and then dark areas and then we
would project light through and then with lenses
make it small and then pl and then project this
onto a substrate and then expose that substrate
to various chemicals with various processes and
the net result was flat transistors. Okay. And
that that really made it a lot easier than sort
of assembling tiny little precise pieces and
that led us to ultimately VLSI design. So let me
show you uh a few artifacts and explain them to
you. So let's start here. This is the Fairchild
2N1613. Let's see if you can see it. Looks kind
of like a spacecraft. It also looks like War
of the Worlds. They used to come through and
scare us. So that is an actual transistor from
1960 which was the first widely available planer
transistor. Before that I've shown you things
like so this Sony radio that I showed you earlier,
this has BJT transistors. Now they don't look all
that different on the outside, but inside they are
constructed very differently. And so let me grab
these Legos here and show you how the BJTs were
constructed. You would get various materials,
right? And then you would you would basically
have to kind of con construct them together
and make like a sandwich. And then you would
con contact wires to make this little sandwich.
And you would connect a wire to the middle part,
the top part, and the bottom part. And that's how
you would make a a BJ a BJT transistor. Okay? So
it's like a Lego block. It's like a stack with
different materials that are in a sense combined
together to make a transistor. Now what they did
instead and I don't really have anything to show
you though to the planer transistor started with
a flat substrate. Okay? And so the flat substrate
would look somewhat like this. This is a piece of
silicon. And then what they would do is they would
sort of paint the lines on it. Then they would
expose it through photoiththography. And then they
would put get circuits and they would cut them
up and they would put each little one inside one
of these transistors. Again, the manufacturing
is not Legoike. It's more painting like spray
painting with masking. Okay. And then that what
that did was that led to making the chips or the
transistors smaller and smaller and smaller and
more VLSI design again that you're going to play
with in this course. This is a 1986 Rockwell
silicon wafer. And on this you can see there's
just about 120 chips. They're about a quarter inch
on each side. Let's zoom in as much as we can.
These transistors are very small, but this is a
100 chips. And then what they would do is they
would come through and they would cut along these
lines and they would solder little tiny wires at
the edge of each of these chips. And then they
would put the chips inside of the package with the
little legs. So, I'm I'm mixing my technologies
here, but here is a Intel 404. And inside this
little tiny package, come on. Little tiny package.
So, you can see this little tiny package. And you
can see the little legs on the tiny package. So,
there were tiny little wires that would It's all
very small. The little chip is inside here. And
then the wires would go from the outside and be
soldered onto the chip and then the chip would
be covered. And that's kind of what this looks
like. And so I can show you a much more modern
chip. And so you can kind of see it. So the the
piece that gets cut out of the silicon wafer on
this AMD processor is here. And then all these
wires and pins eventually find their way to the
inputs and outputs of the actual chip. But these
trans each one of these little quarterinch chips.
Now that was a 2008 processor, but this is a 1986
processor. So that is an example of how photo
lithography can build a lot of chips quickly
with a two-dimensional process. sort of painting
with masks, painting with chemicals and masks that
create these chips that we then cut out and put
into little tiny packages or medium-sized packages
so that we can install them into motherboards
into computers and connect them up to the outside
world. With all of these technologies, transistor
count went crazy. So if you think about 1971,
the Intel 404 had 2,300 transistors. The first
billion transistor chip was the Intel Itanium.
And there's some of these deep learning are are
basically wafer style integration. So you build a
wafer like this and you have these wafers not just
connected. These this wafer was designed to be cut
into pieces, but imagine building a chip that's
the size of a wafer. A deep learning wafer scale
engine by Cababus has 2.6 6 trillion transistors
in 2020. The two terabyte flash memory with 5.3
trillion gates and the Blackwell B1000 B100 CPU
with 208 billion transistors in 2024. So, we've
got a lot and we're starting to create things
that make use of the entire wafer. There's a
lot of complexity and a lot of reliability because
a lot of these chips turn out wrong in the wafer
scale. And so up next, you're going to learn about
VLSI design and how you draw the pictures that
become the patterns that create the gates and the
traces in a chip on one of these silicon wafers.